Finding aid for the University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Geography records UARC.0030
UCLA Library Special Collections
Department of Geography records
1924-1984
UCLA Library Special Collections
University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Geography
UARC.0030
3.2 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
Record Series 30 contains the administrative files of the Department of Geography. These include correspondence of the chair, departmental reports, meeting minutes, Geographic Society meeting minutes, and departmental memoranda. Record Series 30 also contains written accounts of the development of geography education in the University of California system.
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE: Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Geography Department; Transfer; July 1986. Geographic Society newsletters gift of Rosemary and Reese Benson, March 2009.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9935204663606533
Biographical / Historical
Classes in Geography were offered when the Los Angeles State Normal School (now UCLA) opened its doors in 1882. Prior to 1919, when the Los Angeles State Normal School was incorporated into the University of the California system, the department was primarily concerned with the training of secondary school teachers. After 1920 more emphasis was placed on the training of researchers and preparing students for graduate studies. Graduate courses leading to the Masters of Art degree were added to the department curriculum in 1934-1935 and the Doctoral program was added in 1948-1949. In 1985, the Department of Geography was formally established as an academic unit.
Scope and Contents
Record Series 30 contains correspondence files of the chair of the geography department, and administrative materials such as departmental reports, memos and minutes of the Geographic Society. Record Series 30 also contains essays and notes concerning the development of geography education in the University of California system and history of the geography department at UCLA, written by several faculty members.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1924-1984
Series 2: Reports, minutes, and memos, 1924-1983
Series 3: Publications and writings, 1951-1981
Materials in Series 1 are arranged alphabetically. Materials in Series 2 and 3 are arranged chronologically.
Geography -- Study and teaching; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Geography -- Archives
- Correspondence, 1924-1984; Series 1.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 contains correspondence files of the department chair pertaining to the department, the Institute of International and Foreign Studies, the College of Letters and Science, and the Chancellor's Office.
  Arrangement
  This series contains an original alphabetical order, with certain folders containing correspondence solely from particular individuals or organizations. Items are organized alphabetically by the correspondent's last initial, or the first letter in an organizational entity's title. The original order of the files has been maintained.
  - "A", 1931-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "B", 1924-1959, 1960-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Business Office, 1928-1969; 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - "C", 1932-1960, 1961-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "D", 1936-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "E", 1949-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Health and Safety Office, 1958-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "F", 1935-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "G", 1927-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Geography Department - Berkeley, 1958-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Geography Department - Davis, 1961-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Geography Department - Irvine, 1963-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Geography Department - Riverside, 1960-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Geography Department - Santa Barbara, 1960-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Graduate Division, 1933-1944, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "H", 1932-1969, 1970-1983 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - "I", 1941, 1952-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Institute of International and Foreign Studies, 1959-1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "J", 1939-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "K", 1934-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "L", 1936-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - College of Letters and Science, 1930-1969; 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2-5)
  - UCLA Library, 1931-1934; 1958-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Library of Congress, Map Division, 1937, 1951-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "M", 1940-1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - McBride, George, 1942-1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "N", 1953-1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "O", 1927-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "P", 1935-1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - President's Office, 1928-1946, 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Provost's (Chancellor's) Office, 1936-1946, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Q" and "R", 1928-1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "S", 1924-1973 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - "S", 1974-1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Social Science Building, 1941-1953, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "T", 1924-1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "U" and "V", 1931-1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "W", 1925-1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "X", "Y", and "Z", 1941-1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Reports, minutes of meetings, and memos, 1924-1983; Series 2.
  Series 2 contains internal departmental reports, external reviews, memos, and minutes from Geographic Society meetings.
  - Departmental reports, 1924-1953; 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Geographic Society meetings, 1938, 1945-1954 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Departmental memos, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Publications and writings, 1951-1981; Series 3.
  Series 3 contains notes and writings by department professors and staff about the development of geography education in the University of California system and history of the Department of Geography at UCLA.
  - Ruth Baugh, "The beginning of geography in the U.C.", 1951 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Joseph Spencer, "Notes on the growth of the graduate program", 1971 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ruth Baugh and Joseph Spencer, "A historical chronology of the Department of Geography, 1882-1972" (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Joseph Spencer, "Notes on Department Philosophy and Question of Graduate Program", 1973 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Joseph Spencer, "Notes on physical facilities provided the department", 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Gary Dunbar, "Geography in the U.C., 1868-1941," notes, circa 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Gary Dunbar, "Geography in the University of California, 1868-1941", 1981 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters of the Geographic Society, 1941-1950, 1966-1967, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)